<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2025-10-25T23:08:05+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Youssef Al Hariri</title><entry><title type="html">Self-Discipline: A Journey That Begins with a Step and Culminates in Self-Actualization</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/SelfDiscipline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Discipline: A Journey That Begins with a Step and Culminates in Self-Actualization"/><published>2025-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/SelfDiscipline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/SelfDiscipline/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>(An AI translation of the Arabic version)</strong></p> <p>Many of us repeatedly try to improve our direction and move closer to success. Sometimes through deliberate planning, sometimes by instinct. After a realistic plan, discipline and commitment are the two most powerful keys to achievement. Whether that success is academic, professional, physical, or social, every form of progress needs a clear plan and steady effort pursued without fatigue or frustration.</p> <p>Whether you want success in your studies, to follow a healthier lifestyle, to perform routine exercises, or to achieve financial stability. It all begins with a plan and, more importantly, the discipline to follow through. True discipline arises from within and must be renewed whenever you drift from your goals. The journey of success is not a straight climb; it is a series of rises and falls. To strengthen your self-discipline, here are several principles, I tested personally and supported by research studies that consistently prove effective.</p> <h3 id="1-write-down-your-goals-and-tasks-clearly"><strong>1. Write down your goals and tasks clearly</strong></h3> <p>Create a clear, actionable plan that lets you start a task immediately without further decision-making. The more specific and well-linked your plan is, the more likely you are to stay committed and succeed.</p> <p>As James Clear explains in Atomic Habits, an implementation intention can be expressed this way:</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">I will [behavior] at [time] in [place].</code></p> <p>This simple plan carries a powerful sense of commitment—anchored in time and place and integrated into your daily rhythm.</p> <h3 id="2-link-new-habits-to-existing-ones"><strong>2. Link new habits to existing ones</strong></h3> <p>Anchor a new activity to an existing habit—something you already do with little resistance. Although setting this up can feel demanding at first, its impact on consistency is profound.</p> <p>You can expand the implementation intention like this:</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">I will [behavior] at [time] and [place] after [previous habit] and before [next habit].</code></p> <p>This structure reduces mental friction and makes transitions smoother and more automatic. When activities are connected sequentially, you move from one to the next almost effortlessly. If the surrounding tasks are already part of your routine, the new habit fits in naturally and becomes easier to sustain.</p> <p>Remember that rest is also part of discipline. Plan breaks to recharge so your persistence remains steady and sustainable.</p> <h3 id="3-the-five-second-rule"><strong>3. The Five-Second Rule</strong></h3> <p>Mel Robbins’ Five-Second Rule uses a simple countdown—5, 4, 3, 2, 1—to trigger immediate action. It works by creating instant momentum: the countdown shifts your brain into execution mode and reduces hesitation and procrastination.</p> <p>The key is to act immediately once the count ends—without giving yourself time to justify or delay. Repeating the countdown or hesitating defeats the rule’s purpose. Its essence is instant activation that propels you into action before doubt intervenes.</p> <h3 id="4-let-your-results-speak-for-you"><strong>4. Let your results speak for you</strong></h3> <p>Avoid announcing every plan or ambition—let your accomplishments speak. Share goals only with those who will give sincere guidance or constructive feedback. Talking too soon can trick your brain into feeling rewarded before you’ve begun, draining motivation.</p> <p>Repeated talk without execution creates an image of empty promises—both in your mind and in the eyes of others. Work quietly and let progress announce itself. Silent success speaks louder than a thousand declared intentions.</p> <h3 id="5-start-smallreally-small"><strong>5. Start small—really small</strong></h3> <p>Build success through tiny, almost invisible wins. Even the largest structures are the sum of minute parts.</p> <p>Want a reading habit? Start with a single page a day. Want to become a writer? Read a page, then write 50 words daily, linked to an existing habit such as your morning coffee or your evening wind-down.</p> <p>Over time your writing will flow more naturally, your thinking will sharpen, and your efforts will compound. In time you may do in a single evening what once took you a week. Avoid chasing perfection at the start; a marathon in week one of exercise can do more harm than good. Start light, stay consistent, and let growth follow.</p> <h3 id="6-make-your-progress-visible"><strong>6. Make your progress visible</strong></h3> <p>Track achievements, however small. Keep a visible record on a wall calendar or planner where you spend most of your time: your desk, living room, or beside the TV.</p> <p>Seeing progress builds motivation and strengthens commitment. Mark the days you succeed and note reasons for setbacks—this awareness fuels improvement. Over time, visible chains of progress will inspire you not to break the streak. Consistency, not perfection, creates momentum.</p> <h3 id="7-stay-away-from-what-drains-your-energy"><strong>7. Stay away from what drains your energy</strong></h3> <p>People, places, and situations influence behavior—either lifting you or pulling you back. A location might remind you of past failure; a friend might unintentionally disrupt your routine.</p> <p>A good strategy is to minimize exposure to triggers before they arise. Eliminate distractions and reduce contact with what discourages you. Success is not only what you do—it’s also what you avoid. Protecting your focus is an act of discipline.</p> <h3 id="8-use-positive-languagewords-shape-mindset"><strong>8. Use positive language—words shape mindset</strong></h3> <p>Notice the difference between saying I have to and I’m used to.</p> <p>Framing tasks as burdens builds resistance; framing them as choices or habits reinforces empowerment. Instead of saying “I can’t afford that,” try “I’m choosing to invest my money differently.” This subtle shift turns deprivation into control and purpose.</p> <p>The same applies to fitness or health commitments. Instead of viewing exercise as denial, see it as an investment in future health and vitality. Changing vocabulary is not mere linguistic vanity; it is a mental strategy that reshapes how you perceive effort, reward, and growth.</p> <h3 id="9-dont-wait-for-perfect-readinessjust-start"><strong>9. Don’t wait for perfect readiness—just start</strong></h3> <p>Stop waiting for the right time. Most successful people look back and smile at imperfect beginnings—they started consistently, not perfectly. Prepare what you can, do your best with what you have, and act today.</p> <p>You do not need full fluency, complete training, or total confidence to begin. The best time to start was yesterday; the next best time is now.</p> <p>Arabic original of the quotation cited: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">الدُّنْيَا ثَلَاثَةُ أَيَّامٍ: أَمَا أَمْسِ فَقَدْ ذَهَبَ بِمَا فِيهِ، وَأَمَّا غَدًا فَلَعَلَّكَ لَا تُدْرِكُهُ، وَالْيَوْمُ فَاعْمَلْ فِيهِ.</code></p> <p>English rendering: Life is but three days: yesterday has gone with all it held, tomorrow you may not reach, and today is all you truly have—so work in it.</p> <h3 id="in-the-end-discipline-is-a-habit-not-a-talent"><strong>In the end: Discipline is a habit, not a talent</strong></h3> <p>Research and experience agree: success favors the most consistent, not necessarily the most gifted. Self-discipline turns intention into habit and habit into achievement. It is not an innate talent but a cultivated skill built through small steps, sincere perseverance, and a refreshed positive vision.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Self-Discipline: A Journey That Begins with a Step and Culminates in Self-Actualization. __(An AI translation of the Arabic version)__]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Companions on Your Success</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/friendship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Companions on Your Success"/><published>2025-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/friendship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/friendship/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>(An AI translation of the Arabic version)</strong></p> <p>My dear, know that companionship is influential. A friend can either lead you to good or pull you astray. Therefore, choose a companion who eases your path, guides you to goodness, and supports you in times of hardship. This is among the most important values emphasized by Islam, as affirmed in the Qur’an and the Prophetic traditions. Allah Almighty says: <strong>“Close friends, that Day, will be enemies to each other, except for the righteous.”</strong> [Az-Zukhruf: 67]<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p> <p>The Prophet ﷺ also said in the hadith of the seven whom Allah will shade on the Day when there is no shade but His: <strong>“Two men who love each other for the sake of Allah: they meet upon that and part upon that.”</strong><sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p> <p>In this hadith, the Prophet ﷺ urges all Muslims to carefully choose companions who will be beneficial both in this world and the Hereafter. A righteous companion is a source of benefit, while a corrupt one brings harm in both realms.</p> <p>A companion on life’s journey will either be an encourager or a discourager. He may help you rise to noble heights, scale summits, and overcome obstacles—or he may complicate your path, magnify your burdens, weaken your resolve, and beautify failure.</p> <p>Here, I am reminded of Abu Bakr al-Siddiq (may Allah be pleased with him) and his devotion to the companionship of the Prophet ﷺ in all circumstances. Greater still is the Prophet’s own care in choosing him as his companion during the migration to Madinah and their stay together in the cave. How sublime was that noble bond, granting Abu Bakr the honor of companionship in Makkah, in Madinah, and on the blessed migration itself.</p> <p>Is there any comparison between a friend who clarifies your doubts, takes your hand toward success out of love for you, and one who seizes every opportunity to weaken your resolve and turn you away from the path of achievement?</p> <p>Be cautious, for those who seek to harm or sabotage you rarely do so openly. Instead, they may disguise it under the guise of advice or concern. When Satan whispered to our forefather Adam and our mother Hawwa (Eve) to lead them out of Paradise, he swore that he was a sincere adviser: <strong>“And he swore [by Allah] to them, ‘Indeed, I am to you from among the sincere advisors.’”</strong> [Al-A‘raf: 21]<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p> <p>Thus, you must remain vigilant. Strive to choose companions who inspire you to succeed, bring you peace of mind, and increase your self-appreciation—so that your journey toward success becomes a beautiful one, shared with sincere friends.</p> <p>Beware of lending your ear to those who discourage you, or of revealing your distress before them. If you do, you reward them and gladden their hearts—while the only loser is you.</p> <p>And do not assume that disparagement comes only from those below you, or that discouragement arises solely from your superiority or success. Sometimes, the motive is unclear and unjustified. At times, the discourager may even be regarded as a role model or a symbol of success in society. Yet such a person may not hesitate to weaken the determination of those striving behind him. It is as though he seeks to monopolize success for himself and his circle, refusing to share inspiring stories of achievement with others—unless he himself secures the greater share of it.</p> <p>Ironically, such people are well aware that sharing success and making it accessible to others—according to what is called the <em>Abundance vs. Scarcity Mindset</em><sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>—is in fact a means to personal growth, enhanced success, and blessings in knowledge, wealth, and effort. Yet, they withhold it.</p> <p>The impact of success, however, can extend even beyond one’s lifetime. The Prophet ﷺ said: <strong>“When a man dies, his deeds come to an end except for three things: Sadaqah Jariyah (ceaseless charity); a knowledge which is beneficial, or a virtuous descendant who prays for him (for the deceased).”</strong><sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> And as another narration emphasizes: <em>“indeed perhaps one present will inform one who understands better than him.”</em><sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote">6</a></sup></p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Qur’an, Surah Az-Zukhruf, verse 67. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Narrated by Abu Huraira: The Prophet ﷺ said, <em>“Seven will be shaded by Allah under His shade on the Day when there will be no shade except His: a just ruler; a youth who grows up in the worship of Allah; a man whose heart is attached to the mosques; two men who love each other for the sake of Allah, meeting and parting upon that; a man who is called by a woman of status and beauty, and says, ‘I fear Allah’; a man who gives charity so secretly that his left hand does not know what his right hand has given; and a man who remembers Allah in solitude, and his eyes overflow with tears.”</em> Narrated by al-Bukhari and Muslim. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Qur’an, Surah Al-A‘raf, verse 21. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote"> <p>The Abundance vs. Scarcity Mindset: <em>Abundance</em> is the belief that opportunities and blessings are sufficient for everyone, while <em>Scarcity</em> is the belief that resources are limited and one’s success comes only at the expense of others. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Narrated by Muslim. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Narrated by al-Bukhari from Abdullah ibn Umar (may Allah be pleased with them both). <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Islam,"/><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Impact of Companions on Your Success]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving from Conda to Python Virtual Environments</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/Conda2Python/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving from Conda to Python Virtual Environments"/><published>2025-08-16T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-16T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/Conda2Python</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2025/Conda2Python/"><![CDATA[<p>Anaconda has updated its license terms in March 2024, and the updates began to be effectively applied since mid-July 2025. These updates have created a fundamental shift for research institutions, government organizations, and companies that have more than 200 employees. While Anaconda exempts companies with number of employees equal to or less than a threshold of 200 employee and excludes educational institutions that use its products within thier educational curricula (for teaching and learning), it requires others to purchase the required license, including research uses or any use outside the scope of education in educational institutions. As a result, many engineers and researchers looked for alternatives to maintain data and information flow and thus maintain workflow and productivity.</p> <p>Although the open-source Conda tool is still available for free use by everyone, using the default channel (Conda’s default channel) to install libraries is subject to the usage terms applied to Anaconda in terms of the necessity of purchasing a license for use by companies, entities, and institutions whose number of employees exceeds the 200-employee threshold. As solutions to these requirements, the Conda tool can be used with the open-source community channels like conda-forge to install libraries. Additionally, alternative distributions to conda such as Miniforge or Mamba can be installed, which are not subject to the commercial licensing.</p> <p>The problem with these channels is that they do not enjoy the protection and security advantages provided by managed and supported packages from Conda’s default channel. Although there is debate about the impact of this on user data and the reliability of open-source packages, data protection remains sensitive for companies and institutions that care about protecting their data and avoiding the use of tools that are not reviewed or managed by trusted entities like Anaconda.</p> <p>In this space, I would like to present an available alternative that avoids or at least reduces the drawbacks of community channels from Conda, which is using virtual environments directly using Python. These are the same steps I followed to transition from Conda to environments from the base version of Python.</p> <p>First, it’s better to copy the existing environments on your device from Conda. To do this, you need to activate the virtual environment, then extract the packages/libraries that were installed in that virtual environment. After copying these packages, Anaconda can be completely removed, and all files associated with it can be removed from your device.</p> <p>After that, you can install the required version of Python from the official website (https://www.python.org/). While the ideal case is installing the latest version to benefit from the latest security updates and improvement advantages, previous versions can be chosen if they are compatible with necessary packages or libraries for work. Multiple versions can also be installed on the device. In this example, we installed two versions of Python: Python 3.13.7 and Python 3.11.0. To know the default version on the device, from the Command Prompt (cmd), you can enter the command python -V, while to use the other version, you need to use the full path, as shown in the following command:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>C:<span class="se">\P</span>YTHON_INSTALLATION_PATH<span class="se">\P</span>ython<span class="se">\P</span>ython311<span class="se">\p</span>ython.exe <span class="nt">-V</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Following the same method, you can create the required virtual environment. For example, to create a virtual environment based on Python 3.13 and name it venv_3.13, we will write the following command in the command prompt:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python <span class="nt">-m</span> venv venv_3.13
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To create a virtual environment based on Python 3.11 and name it venv_3.11, we will enter the command in the command prompt (replacing PYTHON_INSTALLATION_PATH with the path used to install Python 3.11 version):</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="s2">"C:</span><span class="se">\P</span><span class="s2">YTHON_INSTALLATION_PATH</span><span class="se">\P</span><span class="s2">ython</span><span class="se">\P</span><span class="s2">ython311</span><span class="se">\p</span><span class="s2">ython.exe"</span> <span class="nt">-m</span> venv venv_3.11
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Please note that the created environment will be created in the folder where the command pointer is located, so attention should be paid to ensure the pointer is in the intended folder, and it can be in the root folder of the project. In this case, the folder should be added to the folders that are ignored if the project is within version control system tools like GitHub.</p> <p>To activate the created environment, you can enter the following command:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>venv_3.13<span class="se">\S</span>cripts<span class="se">\a</span>ctivate
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To verify the Python version used in the activated environment, we enter the following command:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python <span class="nt">-V</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>We will notice that the Python version in the version specific to the activated environment is version 3.13.7.</p> <p>You can then use the pip library to install the required packages and libraries.</p> <p>To deactivate the virtual environment, you can write the command:</p> <div class="language-shell highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>deactivate
</code></pre></div></div> <p>And the virtual environment will be deactivated.</p> <p>While managing virtual environments in this method does not provide all the advantages of Conda in managing packages, libraries, and dependencies, you can use additional open-source tools to bridge this gap, such as:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pip-tools</code>: A tool for installing and managing dependencies precisely with version pinning.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Poetry</code>: An integrated package and environment manager for Python that combines virtual environment creation, dependency management, and project building for deployment.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virtualenvwrapper</code>: A tool for easily managing multiple virtual environments from the command prompt.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Virtual"/><category term="environments"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from Conda to Python Virtual Environments. (AI translation version from the Arabic version - reviewed).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arab societies in Western-based research studies.. Unacquaintance or Disregarding?</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ResearchersBiased/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arab societies in Western-based research studies.. Unacquaintance or Disregarding?"/><published>2024-09-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ResearchersBiased</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ResearchersBiased/"><![CDATA[<p>From my reading in some research, I have found a widespread phenomenon among Western researchers: they either ignore or overlook an important fact in the Arab and Muslim societies, which is the importance of social and emotional bonding among the individuals within the community and cross other communities. It is easy to sense their lack of understanding of the reasons behind certain answers in their survey studies, interpreting them as negative phenomena. They overlook or ignore the fact that it is essential to place these phenomena within the social, cultural, and religious context to understand their importance for Muslims or Arabs to build a cohesive and healthy society. The disaster is that when they link these phenomena to values and customs that were known in their heritage but have been vanished under what is called development and modernity. In this case, the situation worsens, and the interpretations become more gloomy.</p> <p>For example, in my recent reading of the book “Religion’s Sudden Decline: What’s Causing it, and What Comes Next?” by Ronald F. Inglehart, I noticed the biased interpretations of the author towards the societies of the Scandinavian countries and the high-income countries as societies that are more open to strangers, and that societies in all predominantly Muslim countries are closed and less accepting of strangers.</p> <p>The author deduced this from a survey of a sample from various countries. For example, in a question about the religion of the neighbor, the author found that 31% of the sample in predominantly Muslim countries do not want their neighbors to be of a different religion, while only 4% from the Scandinavian countries and 6% from the “rich” countries have the same stance toward neighbors. These percentages slightly increase in the answer to the question about having neighbors who are immigrants or foreign workers, reaching 34% in Muslim countries and 9% in Scandinavian countries. The percentage increases significantly in the more embarrassing and important questions, as 32% of the sample from the Scandinavian countries and 80% from the predominantly Muslim countries agreed that employers should prioritize citizens over immigrants in obtaining jobs in the case of jobs’ shortages.</p> <p>However, it is worth noting that while societies in non-Muslim countries appear more open to accepting others, they seem less open to the internal community, the family, and especially the relationship between parents and children. Only 9% of the sample from the Scandinavians and 23% from the high-income countries strongly agreed that one of the main goals of their lives is to make their parents proud of them, while the 71% from the Muslim countries have the same stance. This reflects the family bond between parents and children in Muslim societies. The question is, does the detachment from the natural relationship between parents and their children indicates a modermnity, development and the integration of the society and the openness of its individuals to others?</p> <p>More strangely, 24% of citizens from the Scandinavian north and 48% from the rich (non-Muslim) countries considered that it necessary for children to provide care for their parents when they are ill and in-need of care. However, 87% of citizens from predominantly Muslim countries considered caring for parents is a duty of the children when they are ill. Finally, 71% of citizens from Muslim countries considered having children is a societal responsibility towards their communities, compared to only 11% of citizens from the Scandinavian countries and 21% from the rich countries who see it that way.</p> <p>The contradiction between the two results is truly surprising. How can it be consistent that those who do not care about their parents are more open to strangers and their right to obtain jobs even if there is a shortage in the job market in their country? In the Arabic culture, it has been said: “There is no good in one who has no good for his family.” It seems that most Western researchers who advocate modernity and development do not understand or at least neglect the social, psychological, and even economic benefits of the strong bonds among the individuals within the society, which is vital characteristic at the Muslim and Arabic communities. In the context of Islam, which usually has misinterpreted, we recall the saying of the Prophet Muhammad, peace be upon him, “The best among you are those who are best to their families, and I am the best to my family.” And as the poet Jihad Jaha said: “The one who has no good for his family Certainly has no good for others so know this. Whoever expects affection from him Is like expecting the taste of sweets from bitterness.”</p> <p>Therefore, I see it as a duty for Arab and Muslim researchers and critics to focus on the importance of contextualizing matters. The data indicates that citizens in Muslim countries have a sense of belonging and connection with the family and community, which is a matter of pride and significance for the well-being of the individual and society, even if those deceived by modernity claim otherwise. Thus, the characteristics that one seeks in a neighbor are important in the Muslim community because of the duties and obligations that arise from their presence nearby, in accordance with the social conditions and nature of the communities. If not for the commitment to what is stated in Islam about the importance of caring for the neighbor as Allah Almighty said: “Worship Allāh and associate nothing with Him, and to parents do good, and to relatives, orphans, the needy, the near neighbor, the neighbor farther away, the companion at your side,1 the traveler, and those whom your right hands possess. Indeed, Allāh does not like those who are self-deluding and boastful.” And as the Prophet Muhammad, peace be upon him, said “Gabriel kept advising me to be good to neighbors until I thought he would make them my heirs.” Indeed, the neighbor has duties and rights known to the Arabs even before Islam, as Antarah al-Absi said: “I protect the neighbor from every disgrace, And rejoice with the guest who stays and cheer.”</p> <p>Therefore, the characteristics that a person seeks in a neighbor include origin, beliefs, social and financial status to make community integration more natural and neighbors more affiliated with each other, which is promoted and sought by most societies in predominantly Muslim countries. While this affiliation decreases in non-Muslim countries and societies, it affects not only the relationship with the neighbor but also includes parents and children and the limited nature of duties and commitments between individuals, transforming them into rights and commitments between the individual and the social system as a whole rather than the individual, family, and the smaller community within the neighborhood, and Allah is the helper.</p> <p>(This text is a manually modified version from the automatics translated version of the Arabic by using AI, ChatGPT).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Family,"/><category term="Communities,"/><category term="Relationships"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Arab societies in Western-based research studies.. Unacquaintance or Disregarding?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The lack of deep relationships in the age of social media</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Families/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The lack of deep relationships in the age of social media"/><published>2024-08-02T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Families</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Families/"><![CDATA[<p>Educational and psychological experts differentiate relationships as either superficial or deep. Alarmingly, some describe a superficial relationship as one where you need to ask the other party about regular details of their life, whether these details are important, urgent, or routine. This could be a parent asking their child about their meals or studies upon meeting them or children asking their parents about their meals or medications only upon seeing them instead of having an ongoing regular follow-up.</p> <p>Conversely, a deep relationship is one in which a person can always answer about it when they are with them, seeks answers when apart, and feels the need to meet or stay in touch with them most frequently. This is the deep relationship, where both parties feel a sense of belonging and constant connection.</p> <p>Shockingly, as presented above, most of our family relationships are superficial, even if we claim otherwise!</p> <p>Furthermore, in these times, we need to deepen our relationships with our children, parents, siblings and spouses. We should ask ourselves, when was the last time one of your children shared their thoughts openly without fear of the consequences? When was the last time you understood their needs without declaring it? And when did you last respond to your kid’s question with the utmost attention? When was the last time they noticed that they caught your attention? For example, you looked directly at them while they were asking, you received their question with interest as if it was from someone important, engaged with their inquiries, discussed their ideas and searched with them for answers to their questions.</p> <p>We may force ourselves to interact nicely with a child’s question. Still, the discussion may soon turn into a heated debate, prompting the children to end the conversation or pretend they understood the answer. Often, this is because we expect reverence toward parents instead of merely respecting them, and this reverence is seen as an integral part of our duty to them. Thus, the children fear their parents, and through their experiences, they avoid discussing their secrets and problems with them, and the disaster is when this becomes widespread among the community. This results in fragmented families, connected only by necessity and need. Families lack a blessed good relationship, where children enjoy their time with their parents and vice versa. Suppose a son or daughter finds someone who provides them with perceived affection through social media, at school, or in the neighbourhood. In that case, they often gravitate towards them—not out of hatred for their families or ignorance of the dangers, but in search of affection and love and a deep relationship where they can act spontaneously and which responds to their inquiries and needs, even if it is illusory. Chasing mirages is typical of the thirsty. More sadly, children may grow distant from their parents and their siblings. After marriage, they become separate groups, brought together only on social occasions or by the minimum commitment enforced by law or traditions. The opportunity to build ties among and with them has passed, their needs have been satisfied by others, or it has been completely closed off, and this suffering may pass on to future generations.</p> <p>Note: this is a manually modified version of an English generated version of the Arabic article by using AI.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Family,"/><category term="Relationships"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The lack of deep relationships in the age of social media]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Failures are lessons for a brighter future</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Failures are lessons for a brighter future"/><published>2024-07-26T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-26T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Failures are lessons for a brighter future]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adding Virtual Environment</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding Virtual Environment"/><published>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments/"><![CDATA[<p>In this article, I will explain how to avoid the limitations associated with creating a virtual environment using a specific version of Python, particularly when root privileges are unavailable for installing that version. This guidance is essential for those needing to work within constrained software environments. This article provides useful steps to solve the failure of the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python3.8 -m venv venv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This approach is particularly important for objectives such as avoiding libraries’ compatibility issues. The solution I discuss involves using a conda virtual environment with the desired version of Python. If conda is not already installed on your system, it can be downloaded from the Conda website[https://docs.conda.io/projects/conda/en/latest/user-guide/install/index.html]. For the purposes of this example, Python version 3.8 is required.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda create -n temp python=3.8
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After creating the conda environment, we need to activate it:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda activate temp
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, we need to install the virtual environment library:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>pip install virtualenv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>By completing this step successfully, we can use the library (virtualenv) with Python3.8 version to create the new virtual environment (venv) in the system as follows:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>virtualenv -p $(which python3.8) venv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, we need to deactivate the conda virtual environment, temp, and then activate the newly created virtual environment (venv).</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda deactivate
source venv/bin/activate
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now, to test the Python version in the virtual environment, we use the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python --version
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The expected output is something similar to the following:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Python 3.8.##
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Where the ‘hashes’ refer to the Python’s patch version number. To ensure that the current Python version is in the virtual environment (venv) and not located in another path, use the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>which python
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The output should include the folder, where (venv) is the name of the virtual environment:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>./venv/bin/python
</code></pre></div></div> <p>By reaching this, we have successfully created a virtual environment with a specific version of Python without having it installed in the system and without having the root access privileges to install that version of Python in the system.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Virtual"/><category term="environments"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Adding virtual environment with specific version of Python.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You can’t control the wind, but you can adjust the sails.</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/life_messages1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You can’t control the wind, but you can adjust the sails."/><published>2024-07-19T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-19T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/life_messages1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/life_messages1/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(Messages) You can't control the wind, but you can adjust the sails.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific integrity</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific integrity"/><published>2024-07-12T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scientific integrity]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision 2?</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision 2?"/><published>2024-07-05T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision?]]></summary></entry></feed>