<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2024-07-26T15:14:19+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Youssef Al Hariri</title><entry><title type="html">Adding Virtual Environment</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding Virtual Environment"/><published>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/virtualEnvironments/"><![CDATA[<p>In this article, I will explain how to avoid the limitations associated with creating a virtual environment using a specific version of Python, particularly when root privileges are unavailable for installing that version. This guidance is essential for those needing to work within constrained software environments. This article provides useful steps to solve the failure of the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python3.8 -m venv venv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This approach is particularly important for objectives such as avoiding libraries’ compatibility issues. The solution I discuss involves using a conda virtual environment with the desired version of Python. If conda is not already installed on your system, it can be downloaded from the Conda website[https://docs.conda.io/projects/conda/en/latest/user-guide/install/index.html]. For the purposes of this example, Python version 3.8 is required.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda create -n temp python=3.8
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After creating the conda environment, we need to activate it:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda activate temp
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, we need to install the virtual environment library:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>pip install virtualenv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>By completing this step successfully, we can use the library (virtualenv) with Python3.8 version to create the new virtual environment (venv) in the system as follows:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>virtualenv -p $(which python3.8) venv
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, we need to deactivate the conda virtual environment, temp, and then activate the newly created virtual environment (venv).</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda deactivate
source venv/bin/activate
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now, to test the Python version in the virtual environment, we use the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python --version
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The expected output is something similar to the following:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Python 3.8.##
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Where the ‘hashes’ refer to the Python’s patch version number. To ensure that the current Python version is in the virtual environment (venv) and not located in another path, use the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>which python
</code></pre></div></div> <p>The output should include the folder, where (venv) is the name of the virtual environment:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>./venv/bin/python
</code></pre></div></div> <p>By reaching this, we have successfully created a virtual environment with a specific version of Python without having it installed in the system and without having the root access privileges to install that version of Python in the system.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Virtual"/><category term="environments"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Adding virtual environment with specific version of Python.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Failures are lessons for a brighter future</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Failures are lessons for a brighter future"/><published>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/futureLessions/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Failures are lessons for a brighter future]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific integrity</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific integrity"/><published>2024-07-12T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/integrity/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scientific integrity]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision 2?</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision 2?"/><published>2024-07-05T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness2/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Habits stacking</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsStacking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Habits stacking"/><published>2024-06-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsStacking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsStacking/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Habits stacking]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision?</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision?"/><published>2024-06-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/happiness1/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it really life is a choice and happiness is a decision?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Implementation intention</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ImplementationIntention/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Implementation intention"/><published>2024-06-13T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-13T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ImplementationIntention</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/ImplementationIntention/"><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits,"/><category term="Islam"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Implementation intention]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Habits In Islam</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsInIslam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Habits In Islam"/><published>2024-06-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsInIslam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/HabitsInIslam/"><![CDATA[<p>Islam is concerned with the education of the individual and society by paying attention to habits, no matter how small they are. Allah Almighty said, “ So whoever does an atom’s weight of good will see it. And whoever does an atom’s weight of evil will see it.” (verses 7 and 8 of Surat Az-Zalzalah). The Almighty said, “And the record [of deeds] will be placed [open], and you will see the criminals fearful of that within it, and they will say, ‘Oh, woe to us! What is this book that leaves nothing small or great except that it has enumerated it?’ And they will find what they did present [before them]. And your Lord does injustice to no one”. The Almighty Creator even urged His Prophet to pay attention to the purity of the body and clothing from the physical abomination and the purification of the soul from the mental abomination by abandoning abomination and idols, although the reader may think that the former is unrelated to the latter. The verses linked physical purity and spiritual purity to takbir and determination on the path of da’wah, saying: “ O you who covers himself [with a garment]. Arise and warn. And your Lord glorify. And your clothing purify. And uncleanliness(1) avoid.”</p> <p>The Holy Prophet, peace be upon him, also emphasized the need to increase good habits, no matter how small they are, and to stay away from bad habits, no matter how considered tiny. The prophet said: “Do good deeds properly, sincerely and moderately and know that your deeds will not make you enter Paradise, and that the most beloved deed to Allah is the most regular and constant even if it were little.”. He even warned against despising the tiny bad deeds, without harsh scolding the sinners, but rather as a leader to survive the calamities of this world and the Hereafter. The Prophet (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) said, “Fear Allah wherever you are, follow a bad deed with a good deed and it will erase it, and behave with good character towards people.” The Messenger of Allah, may Allah bless him and his family and companions and peace be upon him, said: “Guard yourself against the Hellfire, even with half of a date in charity. If one cannot find it, then with a kind word.” The Messenger of Allah (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) said: “Beware of minor offences, like people who descend into the bottom of a valley. One comes with log after log until they bake their bread. Verily, when the one who persistently committed minor sins is taken to account for them, they will ruin him.”</p> <p>The Prophet (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) recommended to Abu Dharr al-Ghaffari (may Allah be pleased with him): “I instruct you to fear Allah in your private and public affairs. If you do a bad deed, then do a good deed. Do not ask anyone for anything, even if you drop your whip. Do not violate what is entrusted, and do not take a position as judge between two people.” All of these are what people have taken for granted in this time, and Allah is the one who helps us.</p> <p>The Prophet (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him and his family and companions) said, “ The five (daily) prayers and from one Friday prayer to the (next) Friday prayer, and from Ramadhan to Ramadhan are expiations for the (sins) committed in between (their intervals) provided one shuns the major sins.” Adhering to perform obligatory prayers, which are repeated five times daily, the Friday prayers every week, and the fasting of Ramadan with faith will expiate minor sins.</p> <p>The Prophet (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) urged Muslims to clean their mouths with Miswak (tooth stick) before every prayer. The Prophet urged his companions to observe the nightly prayer of Witr (one Raka’a), he also urged sleeping in purity and urged adhkar (prays, du’as and remembrances) in various daily activities of Muslim individuals, all of which can be seen as habits that promote success; while these are Islamic devotions that encourage, assist, and promote success in this world and the hereafter.</p> <p>(1) Specifically, idols or generally, bad conduct and morals.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits,"/><category term="Islam"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Habits In Islam]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Habits…Opportunities and Pitfalls</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Habits1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Habits…Opportunities and Pitfalls"/><published>2024-05-30T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Habits1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/Habits1/"><![CDATA[<p>Many writers have signalised the importance of habits, especially micro habits, or so-called atomic habits, due to their importance in shaping our personality, identity, and future. They considered them as an accurate and continuous vote on the personality that one seeks to achieve. The concept of atomic habits has been used by many writers, the most famous of whom is James Clear, the author of “Atomic Habits, Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones”. In his book, he shares his sensational experience in surviving an accident that almost killed his ambition in life, especially his athletic ambition. Instead, he turned it into a dazzling and inspiring success by focusing on acquiring good daily habits, which we usually neglect amid life’s concerns, annoyances, and achievements, whether big or small. Who would think, for example, that daily attention to the bed and organizing the bedroom would positively affect physical health, fitness or achievement? Who would think that attention to the type of clothing would improve job performance or even athletic achievement?</p> <p>Charles Duhigg, the author of the book “The Power of Habit: Why We Do What We Do in Life and Business”, is one of the authors who highlights the importance of habits and how to successfully acquire and maintain the good ones and get rid of the bad ones. It is an inspiring and enriching book in that field and contains a lot of scientific experiments involving the importance of habits. Duhigg explains the importance of the loop (cue → routine → reward) in the continuation of a habit and the importance of breaking that loop to get rid of our bad habits or create them to acquire good habits. Another book, “The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People” by Stephen Covey, lists a set of practices, or habits, commonly practised by successful families and successful people. Although he lists these practices in a way that is far from being related to atomic or micro habits, I thought it was important to mention that aspect.</p> <p>One of the most relevant books is “Make Your Bed: Little Things That Can Change Your Life…And Maybe the World” by Admiral William McRaven. The book helps its readers face failure and loss with the courage needed to build the strength to get up and move on. The importance of considering major successes and achievements not as the result of an isolated heroic act or a moment of triumph separate from the daily routine of life. Rather, they are the results of a series of daily persistence in the face of routine challenges, resisting the tendency to laziness and giving in to failures in those daily routines. It also considers adhering to these small daily routines as a part of major successes and a way to reach them; even if the latter are delayed. Furthermore, the sense of accomplishment in performing these small tasks motivates us to reach the delayed major ones. The book does not only push the readers to the limits of their potential but also to exceed it by paying attention to the usual or usually neglected details of daily life. Hence, accomplishing them becomes an asset and a stepping stone to other successes. The book contains practical advice that reflects the author’s experience, accompanied by inspiring stories from his own life and personal experiences as a member of the US Navy SEALs.</p> <p>Nevertheless, American psychologist William James was the first to note the importance of habits on the individual and society. He considered that living beings are nothing but “bundles of habits” and that 99% of human activity occurs due to habits. He even stated that all our lives are nothing but a pile of practical, emotional and intellectual habits that are systematically organized and carry us irresistibly towards our destiny, whatever the latter may be. While writers have emphasized the importance of habits in the development of human life, especially in enhancing the efficiency of our mental and social abilities, they have also warned of their danger, as the Swiss philosopher Carl Hilty considered that the main issue of life lies in bad habits. He emphasized that humans must have good habits to fight the battles of life.</p> <p>In this series of articles, I will recount the importance of habits and the need to commit to improving them as a new lifestyle, giving examples that will make it easier for readers to start applying these skills to transform habits from weaknesses to strengths. I will also share some of the most effective strategies researchers and writers have come up with to acquire good habits and get rid of bad ones, such as ‘Habit stacking’ and ‘Implementation intention’, just to name some.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Self-reflection,"/><category term="Habits"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Habits...Opportunities and Pitfalls]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Utilizing Langflow to generate a Chat-bot</title><link href="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/LangFlow-First-step/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Utilizing Langflow to generate a Chat-bot"/><published>2024-05-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/LangFlow%20-%20First%20step</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yalhariri.github.io/blog/2024/LangFlow-First-step/"><![CDATA[<p>Artificial intelligence tools including Langflow facilitate the creation of AI-based applications, including the automated dialogue program, aka chat-bots. Hereby, I summarize the steps to implement this using Langflow library.</p> <p>Taken into consideration performing the following:</p> <p>1- Conda virtual environment with Python==3.10</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>conda create -n langflow python==3.10
conda activate langflow 
</code></pre></div></div> <p>2- Ollama serve is installed and running in your machine with the model llama3 pulled.</p> <h2 id="installing">Installing</h2> <p>To install the Langflow, we are going to utilize the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pre released version</code> by using the following command:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python -m pip install langflow --pre --force-reinstall
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After installing it, we need to run it as explained in the following point.</p> <h2 id="running-the-server">Running the server:</h2> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python -m langflow run
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After running the langflow serve, we can access it from the web-based interface. The default link and port of the service is: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">http://127.0.0.1:7860</code>.</p> <h2 id="creating-a-new-project">Creating a new project:</h2> <p>As a start point, let us create a new project. To do so, click on the New Project button.</p> <div style="text-align:center"><video src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/yalhariri/yalhariri.github.io/main/_posts/assets/Langflow_creatingNewProject.mp4" controls="controls" style="max-width: 800px;"> </video></div> <h2 id="adding-the-chat-bot-components">Adding the chat-bot components:</h2> <p>Langflow provides many options for the inputs, models and outputs. In this introduction example, we will use the Ollama model, with model llama3, and the text input with specifying the context by using the prompt component.</p> <p>From the Core Component list, we then can add the following components:</p> <h3 id="1--inputs--chat-input">1- Inputs .. Chat input.</h3> <p>Add the Chat input component.</p> <h3 id="2--inputs--prompt">2- Inputs .. Prompt.</h3> <p>After adding the prompt, you need to configure the prompt’s feature. To perform that, you need to add the template with the desired configurations. In our example, we add the context and the question. To do that, click on template and type in the following lines:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Please answer the question within the context provided.

Context:{context}

Question:{question}
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This will create two inputs: the context and question. The input of the question is the output of the Chat input, to perform that you need to wire the output of the chat input to the question input of the prompt. While the context is a description sentence which you need to add to describe the context of the question, so the model generates a coherent and relevant response for each question.</p> <h3 id="3--models--ollama---llama3-the-mode-llama3-should-be-pulled-in-into-your-system">3- Models .. Ollama - llama3 (the mode llama3 should be pulled in into your system.)</h3> <p>Before making it functional, Ollama service must be up in your machine, and the llama3 model should be pulled. Next, from the Models core component list, add Ollama, and configure the model name to llama3. Finally, it may require adding the Base URL for the model. To perform that, from the Ollama component in the canvas, click on the three dots (…), and then select Advanced. Finally add the Base URL. The default settings for the Ollama is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">http://localhost:11434</code></p> <h3 id="4--outputs--chat-output">4- Outputs .. Chat output.</h3> <p>This component print out the resulted text from the models to the user.</p> <p>After completing the four steps above, click on the Playground to try the chat-bot.</p> <p>At the end, the components in the canvas should look like the following picture.</p> <div style="text-align:center"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/yalhariri/yalhariri.github.io/main/_posts/assets/chat_bot.png" width="800px" alt="Langflow sample Chat-bot"/></div> <p>You can try the following two examples of the context:</p> <p>Example 1:</p> <blockquote> <p>Explain your answer in the same language of user questions. Make your answer clear, concise, and to the point.</p> </blockquote> <p>Example 2:</p> <blockquote> <p>You are a professional interpreter. You receive the sentences from the user, identify the language, and then translate them into English and send them back to the user. In case of ambiguity, provide both translations.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>This example shows how to generate a chat-bot that uses Llama3 model. Langflow provides a large library of models including Amazon Bedrock, Azure OpenAI, Hugging Face API … etc. It also provides other functionalities including helpers such as chat memories, import URLs as a context, and vector stores and searches … etc.</p> <h2 id="extra-resources">Extra resources:</h2> <p>1- https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RWo4GDTZIsE</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Informatics,"/><category term="LLMs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AI-based Chat-bot using Langflow 1]]></summary></entry></feed>